<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Opheleo</title>
    <link href="https://opheleo.cf/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://opheleo.cf" />
    <updated>2020-06-03T11:27:57+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Iraxel</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://opheleo.cf</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Quite a Gale</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/quite-a-gale/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/quite-a-gale/</id>
            <category term="Poetry"/>

        <updated>2020-05-28T19:38:24+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/13/lightning-strike-the-ground-during-night-time-167755.jpg" alt="" />
                    Lightning striking those tired eyes, Staring dully at the slow heavy clouds, Hanging dark above the fearful fields, Once green now gray in the fading light, Sparking distress in pain soaked hearts, Spongefuls of dark melancholy tragedy, The rains falling steadily without respite, Pretending to appear but hides again, Hope wilting under the onslaught, Petals and leaves burdened by the weight, A thundering waterfall on delicate things, Made for better times and fairer winds. Last Updated: 28 May 2020 Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox 
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/13/lightning-strike-the-ground-during-night-time-167755.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>Lightning striking those tired eyes,</em><br><em>Staring dully at the slow heavy clouds,</em><br><em>Hanging dark above the fearful fields,</em><br><em>Once green now gray in the fading light,</em><br><br><em>Sparking distress in pain soaked hearts,</em><br><em>Spongefuls of dark melancholy tragedy,</em><br><em>The rains falling steadily without respite,</em><br><em>Pretending to appear but hides again,</em><br><br><em>Hope wilting under the onslaught,</em><br><em>Petals and leaves burdened by the weight,</em><br><em>A thundering waterfall on delicate things,</em><br><em>Made for better times and fairer winds.</em></p>
<p class="align-right"><em>Last Updated: 28 May 2020</em></p>
<hr>
<p><!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form --></p>
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Departing</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/the-departing/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/the-departing/</id>
            <category term="Poetry"/>

        <updated>2020-05-02T19:19:36+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/10/woman-standing-near-open-door-about-to-step-outside-2297663.jpg" alt="" />
                    In the departing, Is the beginning, Of the turning, From the light we know. For this we perceive, Deep down in our hearts, Every sorrow comes, Because we first depart. Later come the sighings, The regrets that flow, We would be happier, If we never did go. Staying was such bliss, Sweet intimacy, Why then did we leave, Only now to groan?Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox 
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/10/woman-standing-near-open-door-about-to-step-outside-2297663.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>In the departing,<br> Is the beginning,<br> Of the turning,<br> From the light we know.<br> <br> For this we perceive, <br> Deep down in our hearts,<br> Every sorrow comes, <br> Because we first depart.<br> <br> Later come the sighings,<br> The regrets that flow,<br> We would be happier,<br> If we never did go.<br> <br> Staying was such bliss,<br> Sweet intimacy,<br> Why then did we leave,<br> Only now to groan?</em></p>
<hr><!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Subscribe</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/subscribe/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/subscribe/</id>

        <updated>2020-04-27T18:22:42+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/9/bonding-cold-cozy-dog-374845.jpg" alt="" />
                    Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox 
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/9/bonding-cold-cozy-dog-374845.jpg" alt="" />
                <!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Pursuit of Happiness</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/the-pursuit-of-happiness/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/the-pursuit-of-happiness/</id>
            <category term="Articles"/>

        <updated>2020-04-27T18:34:55+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/8/bonding-cold-cozy-dog-374845.jpg" alt="" />
                    The second paragraph of the United States Declaration of Independence begins with "We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness". Yet even though all of us are self-evidently endowed with the right to pursue happiness, we ought really to ask ourselves if we do know what happiness is, and more importantly how to pursue it. If we are true to ourselves, most of us would agree that perhaps we really do not know&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/8/bonding-cold-cozy-dog-374845.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>The second paragraph of the United States Declaration of Independence begins with "We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and <strong>the pursuit of Happiness</strong>". Yet even though all of us are self-evidently endowed with the right to pursue happiness, we ought really to ask ourselves if we do know what happiness is, and more importantly how to pursue it.</p>
<p>If we are true to ourselves, most of us would agree that perhaps we really do not know what happiness is for very often we pursue what we think it is, only to discover with dismay that what we have pursued and obtained gives but short lived satisfaction. And so, we stumble desperately along a variety of paths in a renewed pursuit, each one ending in one kind of disillusionment after another.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6tikl8t0"><strong>Always alluring but never lasting</strong></h2>
<p>Sometimes, we think we can find happiness by pursuing riches. And we initiate long arduous journeys of investments, or disciplined yet enervating, soul-sucking, mind numbing work. And we get richer only to find that not only are we less happier than before but we really have added to our earlier problems by having now to protect and grow wealth even further. What we thought would bring us happiness has brought us only the envious glances of others less fortunate and the constant worry of how long our state of wealth will last.</p>
<p>Or often we pursue the happiness that comes through a flurry of partying and social engagements. And we soon discover that while the company of others provides great solace from the sordid realities of life, the more such solace is pursued, the less satisfaction it brings. Our own social circles no matter how polished or sophisticated soon reveal themselves to be faulty men and women just like us. Eventually, human nature reveals itself in petty jealousies, cliches, arrogance, quarrels and the million other conditions of being human.</p>
<p>And so we discover that whatever the path of pursuit we choose, whether it be intoxication, sensuality, fame, or entertainment, the more we pursue that path the less pleasure it brings. Happiness seems within our grasp, but it keeps us constantly thirsting for more. And the more we drink of its cup, the more empty we eventually feel. Sometimes, in our mad rush to keep ourselves happy, we end up damaging our health, sometimes our consciences, good names, and instead of happiness we find ourselves living with sadness, guilt, depression, fear, or a myriad other ills.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6til11l1"><strong>Can there be a universal prescription?</strong></h2>
<p>In spite of mankind's various quests over time, lasting happiness remains something mysteriously unattainable. Perhaps, only the creator God who made mankind has the answer to what brings about a happiness which is not short lived, and which has no bitterness accompanying it.</p>
<p>We only have to look to the scriptures for God's prescription for happiness. In the bible, in Chapter 5 of The Gospel according to Mathew, we read the Beatitudes which forms part of the Lord’s Sermon on the Mount. Beatitudes is a term meaning exceedingly great happiness. Our Lord, after he had chosen his disciples, separated them from the crowds, a metaphor for how they were to be separated from the people of the world and their human-oriented thinking, and rather taught them eight divine prescriptions that would bring lasting, no, eternal happiness. These teachings still stand true for every believer in Christ who is called to separate from the world systems of happiness and to seek and find happy satisfaction through a higher path.</p>
<p><strong>Mat 5:1-10<br> </strong>And seeing the multitudes, he went up into a mountain: and when he was set, his disciples came unto him:<br> And he opened his mouth, and taught them, saying,</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after righteousness: for they shall be filled.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are the peacemakers: for they shall be called the children of God.</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness' sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</em></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Observing His teachings closely we realize how diametrically different His prescriptions for happiness are when compared to our ingrained habits of pursuit.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The world says "Pursue riches;" He says "Be poor in spirit."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Pursue laughter; party hard;" He says "Mourn for your sins."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Be cool by behaving arrogantly;" He says "Be meek."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Live loose, fast, and free;" He says "Hunger and thirst after righteousness."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "It's all right to keep all matter of impure thoughts in your hearts;" He says "Be pure in your hearts."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Get back at those who hurt you;" He says "Forgive and be merciful."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Make war against your enemies;" He says "Pursue peace."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The world says "Fit in with the crowd to avoid persecution;" He says "Stand up for right behaviour and be happy when you are persecuted."</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>What kind of way of life is this? Can anyone living in the world even believe that living according to these teachings would bring any kind of happiness let alone lasting happiness? These make sense only in the light of the great eternal promises tied to them as rewards, and in the light of the God who stands as the guarantor of their eternal truths. Consider the greatness of the promises: inheriting the Kingdom of Heaven, inheriting the earth, seeing God, being called the children of God, obtaining mercy, obtaining comfort, being filled.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6tim0212"><strong>Happiness in the Spirit</strong></h2>
<p>The obeying of the Beatitudes is likely to bring scorn and sorrow from the world system and its adherents. But the divine guarantor stands by and fulfils His promises through the work of His invisible Holy Spirit. What one who begins even to incredulously obey soon discovers is a strange divine consolation, a divine joy, something approaching inexpressible happiness welling up within. And so as one continues to strive according to these prescriptions, these promised blessings becomes strangely real though still unexplainable to anyone watching. It appears folly and yet it is not. It is but a foretaste of the rewards of faith that keeps one going on ahead in the pursuit in spite of the difficulties that stand in the way. And as one continues trying through repeated failures, the Teacher pours out a divine, equally inexpressible strength to live out this impossible calling.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6timft93"><strong>The Beatitudes and the Sermon on the Mount</strong></h2>
<p>One way or the other, the beatitudes in the Lord’s Sermon on the Mount are mind-blowing. Many who read them walk away scoffing at their seeming foolishness, but those who have begun to appreciate the wisdom and divinity of the Teacher begin to live out these teachings and enjoy a growing rather than diminishing state of inexpressible happiness.</p>
<p>However, all who seek to implement the teachings of the mount must also keep in mind the other mount, the mount of Calvary. Writer and Roman Catholic Archbishop, Fulton J Sheen, in his book The Life of Christ, says "<i>The day Our Lord taught the Beatitudes, He signed His own death warrant. The sound of nails and hammers digging through human flesh were the echoes thrown back from the mountainside where He told men how to be happy or blessed.</i>"</p>
<p>The teaching of one mount comes paired with the suffering of the other. Anyone who seeks to be a disciple of the Lord will experience that even as his master was persecuted, so will he be persecuted. His rejection will overflow into our lives; the insults that missed His ears will fall on our ears; there will be scorn and ridicule; and were one to follow this so completely that the Heavenly Father considers him or her worthy, there may even be martyrdom.</p>
<p>So discovered the early disciples, who had the crown of martyrdom pressed onto their heads, and we consider them exceedingly blessed. May God bless us all too in his coming Kingdom even as we seek to understand and apply the Beatitudes in our own reconfigured pursuit of happiness.</p>
<p class="align-right"><em>Last Updated: 27 April 2020</em></p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Death and Life, Two Sides of the Same Coin</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/death-and-life-two-sides-of-the-same-coin/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/death-and-life-two-sides-of-the-same-coin/</id>
            <category term="Articles"/>

        <updated>2020-04-27T18:35:22+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/7/man-in-black-jacket-standing-in-front-of-grave-3648309.jpg" alt="" />
                    Today, people across the world are locked down by dread of a virus that they cannot see easily. What can be seen however are the frightening graphs of infections and deaths, and the sobering projections of swathes of many more people, countless more, who could die, and die tragically. At a time like this, amidst the fear and gloom for loved ones and self alike, for the economic future, and for the many other uncertainties that lie ahead, one's thoughts turn to a subject that is normally not top of mind. Rising from beneath the covers to which it is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/7/man-in-black-jacket-standing-in-front-of-grave-3648309.jpg" alt="" />
                <!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<p>Today, people across the world are locked down by dread of a virus that they cannot see easily. What can be seen however are the frightening graphs of infections and deaths, and the sobering projections of swathes of many more people, countless more, who could die, and die tragically. At a time like this, amidst the fear and gloom for loved ones and self alike, for the economic future, and for the many other uncertainties that lie ahead, one's thoughts turn to a subject that is normally not top of mind.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6m75net1"><strong>The specter of mortality</strong></h2>
<p>Rising from beneath the covers to which it is normally subjected to, the idea of mortality wakes up and walks across one's consciousness. No longer is it shushed and shooed away by the busyness of a usually busy life. It stands around like an uninvited guest not knowing what to do with itself. Yet it cannot leave. The doors are closed.</p>
<p>Mortality. An idea whose time is now. Many who had planned their careers, travel plans, education, or comfortable retirement have felt the icy fingers of death reminding them of that word. Many are no longer around to consider its implications for life on the planet, but many have recovered and cannot forget their close encounter. And like them, for the vast majority of humanity that hasn't had a close call yet, this is a clarion call to remind themselves of that word. Because, even though the pandemic may pass away sooner or later, that word remains standing around with its timeless truth - everyone dies. One way or another.</p>
<p>So how is one to make sense of one's mortality? Is one to morbidly mope around waiting for the inevitable? Or must one climb the mountains and meditate for an escape route because really who wants to die? Is there an escape route? If yes, where can it be found?</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6m75vme2"><strong>Comfortless answers</strong></h2>
<p>What is being taught in schools and colleges across the world is the so-called science of evolution. We are being told that we evolved from lower life forms and that as a race we continue to evolve. The answers of that logic, to the questions posed by this pandemic, is that individuals do not matter. Hundreds of thousands may die but the race will live on. A vaccine will be found. Herd immunity will develop. This will be wiped out. Those left behind can let out a sigh of relief. For now.</p>
<p>But somehow, those words ring hollow of comfort. If evolution is all there is, what then of individual purpose and meaning? Is this all we scrounge around on the surface of the earth for, as contributors to the progress of the race? Why not live like beasts then for tomorrow we die - surely there must be more!</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6m76c1a3"><strong>God. Eternity.</strong></h2>
<p>So, then we turn to faith and God and eternity. Most do in times of turmoil. Because we eventually discover a buried concept within us that is but the other side of mortality. If mortality means death, then immortality must mean life forever. But can both coexist when all we see is the certainty of death heading towards us like an onrushing wave? Surely, they can. That is if we have eternal spirits, and mortality is merely a transition to a higher state of consciousness. A consciousness that encompasses beings and powers that we are not normally aware of. And so, like many others who have pursued this train of thought, our thoughts turn to gods and our conceptions of them. For if they exist how can we know them? Do we need to know them? If the spiritual plane of consciousness is a reality, why are we so afraid? Is a spiritual reality worse than the world we have known or is it an endless experience of endless delights?</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e6m76p0b4"><strong>Seeking life not death</strong></h2>
<p>The answers to these questions will determine our state of mind as we go through this pandemic. Many have sought these answers but none can claim to have definitively found them. But many have found the solace of faith. Faith comes in different hues, different shapes. But faith comforts as long as it can explain. A child believes it can fly until it falls with a crash when it leaps off a bed. And so, like children, we keep growing in our awareness, shedding our childish beliefs as they fail to prove or explain the realities of our life experiences. We discover laws like gravity, and when we understand the inevitability of those laws, we use them and learn how to really fly. Not in painful ignorance and the inevitable crash, but through understanding and cooperating with those laws we even reach other planets.</p>
<p>And so, even as we go through that process, we realize that this is what life is. A discovery of the physical, and then as we grow older and wiser, the metaphysical truths. We examine the various concepts that spirituality has to offer. Some say this, some say that, but even as a snake sheds its skin, we shed our incorrect conceptions and move into realities and truths that endure. And once having discovered truths that sustain, we continue on to deeper truths. Thus, many claim their faith protects them from plagues and sicknesses, but then from the hospital bed they realize the higher ideas that faith can in the end only save them from diseases of the soul. And so, all of life is about realizing that mortality cannot be cheated. Death is the price to be paid for life. And may God speed us all as we go about discovering these eternal truths. </p>
<p class="align-right"><em>Last updated: April 24, 2020</em></p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Contact</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/contact/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/contact/</id>

        <updated>2020-04-19T21:13:42+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    If you would, please fill out the form below. Loading…
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>If you would, please fill out the form below.</p>
<p><iframe width="640" height="673" src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfI3nNN45mirmA7McRtJmovPKi7Vq8De_XYS9R4Ps9IzNR36g/viewform?embedded=true" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Whats Common Between Greed and Immorality?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/whats-common-between-greed-and-immorality/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/whats-common-between-greed-and-immorality/</id>
            <category term="Articles"/>

        <updated>2020-04-27T21:23:17+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/5/close-up-of-one-us-dollar-3635539.jpg" alt="" />
                    In the epistle to the Colossians, Paul exhorts the believers of that church to consider the members of their earthly bodies as dead to various things: “Consider the members of your earthly body as dead to immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire, and greed, which amounts to idolatry.” - Col 3:5b (NASB) As I read this verse, I was surprised to find greed a part of this list. It was almost like finding an orange in a box of apples. The word greed is the only one that seemingly does not have much to do with sexuality. So, curious, I looked up the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://opheleo.cf/media/posts/5/close-up-of-one-us-dollar-3635539.jpg" alt="" />
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">In the epistle to the Colossians, Paul exhorts the believers of that church to consider the members of their earthly bodies as dead to various things: <i>“Consider the members of your earthly body as dead to immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire, and greed, which amounts to idolatry.”</i> - Col 3:5b (NASB)</span></p>
<p class="p2">As I read this verse, I was surprised to find greed a part of this list. It was almost like finding an orange in a box of apples. The word greed is the only one that seemingly does not have much to do with sexuality. So, curious, I looked up the Greek words used in the original text and their meanings:</p>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">Immorality (Greek: porneia) - illicit sexual intercourse</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">Impurity (Greek: akatharsia) - the impurity of lustful, luxurious, profligate living</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">Passion (Greek: pathos) - used in the NT in a bad sense i.e depraved passion</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">Desire (Greek: epithymia) - used in the NT desire for what is forbidden, lust</span></li>
</ul>
<p class="p2">Wherever these words have been used in the new testament (NT), they always refer to some kind of sexual deviancy either in thought or deed. And so the Colossians list is that of sexual sinfulness descending in order of severity.</p>
<p class="p2">This verse reminded me of another portion in James 1:14,15: <i>“But each one is tempted when he is carried away and enticed by his own lust (epithymia). Then when lust has conceived, it gives birth to sin; and when sin is accomplished, it brings forth death.”</i> In just a similar vein, the descending severity of the list in Colossians could present before the mind a picture of desire<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>conceiving passion, which in turn conceives impurity, which finally conceives immorality. So why then is greed the mother lode of this list when it apparently doesn’t have anything to do with immorality. Or does it?</p>
<p class="p2">The key is found in the phrase, “greed, which amounts to idolatry” or better translated in the KJV as “which is idolatry.” Paul clearly equates greed with idolatry. And it is this equation with idolatry which perhaps explains why greed is the first rung on this ascending ladder of desire.</p>
<p class="p2">The link between Idolatry and immorality is most clearly seen in the passage of Romans 1: 21-32). Watch how the idolatry in v23 begins a downward trajectory:</p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v23 - <i>“...they exchanged the glory of the incorruptible God for an image...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v24 - <i>“....God gave them over in the lusts of their hearts to impurity ...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v25 - <i>“...they exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshiped and served the creature rather than the Creator,...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v26 - <i>“...God gave them over to degrading passions;...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v27 - <i>“...burned in their desire toward one another...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v28 - <i>“...God gave them over to a depraved mind...”</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">v32 - <i>“...they not only do the same, but also give hearty approval to those who practice them.”</i></span></p>
<p class="p2">We also see the same link between idolatry and immorality in the book of Exodus. When Moses was on mount Sinai, the Israelites fashioned an idol of a golden calf for themselves, and called it their god and built it an altar. What happened next is tragic <i>“So the next day they rose early and offered burnt offerings, and brought peace offerings; and the people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play”</i> - Ex 32:6. The phrase “rose up to play” is an euphemism of the sexual immorality that the Israelites had seen and practiced in Egypt. And this after they had witnessed the trumpets, thunder, fire, and quakings of the mountain of God. </p>
<p class="p2">When one sees this downward spiral at play, the seeming harmless sin of greed takes on a new importance. The Greek word for greed, pleonexia, is also translated as coveting. And coveting is expressly prohibited by the last among the ten commandments which in essence says, “Do not covet”.</p>
<p class="p2">Today’s world encourages the breaking of this commandment in its most extreme form. Tantalizing pictures of what we can purchase through EMI’s<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>abound on every street corner, among the pages of every magazine and<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>newspaper, and on every web site one visits. Cars, vacations, houses, gadgets, there just is no end to the articles sold in vanity fair. Coveting what we don’t have and what others have, stokes the flame of desire and before we know it, we are down the road of idolatry and over time given over to immorality. The god of Mammon, the god of money is the most common idol of our times, and we serve this idol thinking it can satisfy the unsatisfiable coveting of our lustful hearts. How merciful God is that He does give us over completely! </p>
<p class="p2">If we then see such clear and dangerous links, let us, as Paul exhorts in this verse, consider the members of our earthly body as dead to greed. How this translates into practical application could mean primarily keeping the mind free of coveting what God in his wisdom has chosen not to give us yet. Of keeping our hands from reaching out for even more money to buy even more things. Of choosing not to use our limited time and resources in the pursuit of the world’s goods at the cost of our physical and spiritual health and relationships.</p>
<p class="p2">Let's keep guard heeding the apostle John who wrote in 1 John 5:21: <i>“Little children, guard yourselves from idols.”</i></p>
<hr><!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://opheleo.us8.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52&amp;id=a96cc76c80" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Subscribe to the latest posts straight to your inbox</label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value="" placeholder="email address"> <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_2b3feaac61d83cee795fbee52_a96cc76c80" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/about/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/about/</id>

        <updated>2020-05-02T21:28:26+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Opheleo is a Greek word which means to help, benefit, or do good. This site hosts of articles and essays and other random writings with the common thread that they're written with a view of being of some use to whoever happens to stumble onto this site. Most of the content is written from a Christian worldview, but having been written by an amateur hobby writer, may not be very theological sound. So read at your own peril, and be a Berean if you know what I mean. Whether you are a believer or a seeker or a disinterested passerby, may you&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Opheleo is a Greek word which means to help, benefit, or do good. This site hosts of articles and essays and other random writings with the common thread that they're written with a view of being of some use to whoever happens to stumble onto this site.  Most of the content is written from a Christian worldview, but having been written by an amateur hobby writer, may not be very theological sound. So read at your own peril, and be a Berean if you know what I mean.</p>
<p>Whether you are a believer or a seeker or a disinterested passerby, may you understand more clearly the purpose of the One who asked long ago: <em>What will it profit a man if he gains the world and forfeits his soul?</em></p>
<p>You can reach out to the author who goes by the pen name Iraxel with bouquets, brickbats, or corrections by using the contact form <a href="../../../../../contact">here</a>.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
