<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Opheleo</title>
    <link href="https://opheleo.cf/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://opheleo.cf" />
    <updated>2020-04-19T19:34:05+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Iraxel</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://opheleo.cf</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Whats Common Between Greed and Immorality?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/whats-common-between-greed-and-immorality/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/whats-common-between-greed-and-immorality/</id>
            <category term="Articles"/>

        <updated>2020-04-19T19:28:12+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In the epistle to the Colossians, Paul exhorts the believers of that church to consider the members of their earthly bodies as dead to various things: “Consider the members of your earthly body as dead to immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire, and greed, which amounts to idolatry.” - Col 3:5b (NASB) As I read this verse, I happened to look up the Greek words used, and I was surprised to find greed a part of this list. It was almost like finding an orange in a box of apples. The word greed is the only one that apparently does not&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1">In the epistle to the Colossians, Paul exhorts the believers of that church to consider the members of their earthly bodies as dead to various things: <i>“Consider the members of your earthly body as dead to immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire, and greed, which amounts to idolatry.”</i> - Col 3:5b (NASB)</p>
<p class="p2">As I read this verse, I happened to look up the Greek words used, and I was surprised to find greed a part of this list. It was almost like finding an orange in a box of apples. The word greed is the only one that apparently does not have much to do with sexuality.</p>
<p class="p2">Immorality (Greek: porneia) - illicit sexual intercourse</p>
<p class="p1">Impurity (Greek: akatharsia) - the impurity of lustful, luxurious, profligate living</p>
<p class="p1">Passion (Greek: pathos) - used in the NT in a bad sense i.e depraved passion</p>
<p class="p1">Desire (Greek: epithymia) - used in the NT desire for what is forbidden, lust</p>
<p class="p2">Wherever these words have been used in the new testament (NT), they always refer to some kind of sexual deviancy either in thought or deed. And so the list is that of sexual sinfulness descending in order of severity.</p>
<p class="p2">This verse reminded me of another portion in James 1:14,15: <i>“But each one is tempted when he is carried away and enticed by his own lust (epithymia). Then when lust has conceived, it gives birth to sin; and when sin is accomplished, it brings forth death.”</i> In just a similar vein, the descending severity of the list in Colossians presents before the mind a picture of desire<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>conceiving passion, which in turn conceives impurity, which finally conceives immorality. So why then is greed the mother lode of this list when it apparently doesn’t have anything to do with immorality. Or does it?</p>
<p class="p2">The key is found in the phrase, “greed, which amounts to idolatry” or better translated in the KJV as “which is idolatry.” Paul clearly equates greed with idolatry. And it is this equation with idolatry which perhaps explains why greed is the first rung on this ascending ladder of desire.</p>
<p class="p2">The link between Idolatry and immorality is most clearly seen in the passage of Romans 1: 21-32). Watch how the idolatry in v23 begins a downward trajectory:</p>
<p class="p1">v23 - <i>“...they exchanged the glory of the incorruptible God for an image...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v24 - <i>“....God gave them over in the lusts of their hearts to impurity ...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v25 - <i>“...they exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshiped and served the creature rather than the Creator,...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v26 - <i>“...God gave them over to degrading passions;...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v27 - <i>“...burned in their desire toward one another...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v28 - <i>“...God gave them over to a depraved mind...”</i></p>
<p class="p1">v32 - <i>“...they not only do the same, but also give hearty approval to those who practice them.”</i></p>
<p class="p2">We also see the same link between idolatry and immorality in the book of Exodus. When Moses was on mount Sinai, the Israelites fashioned an idol of a golden calf for themselves, and called it their god and built it an altar. What happened next is tragic <i>“So the next day they rose early and offered burnt offerings, and brought peace offerings; and the people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play”</i> - Ex 32:6. The phrase “rose up to play” is an euphemism of the sexual immorality that the Israelites had seen and practiced in Egypt. And this after they had witnessed the trumpets, thunder, fire, and quakings of the mountain of God. </p>
<p class="p2">When one sees this downward spiral at play, the seeming harmless sin of greed takes on a new importance. The Greek word for greed, pleonexia, is also translated as coveting. And coveting is expressing prohibited by the last among the ten commandments which in essence says, “Do not covet”. Today’s world encourages the breaking of this commandment in its most extreme form. Tantalizing pictures of what we can purchase through EMI’s<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>abound on every street corner, among the pages of every magazine and<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>newspaper, and on every web site one visits. Cars, vacations, houses, gadgets, there just is no end to the articles sold in vanity fair. Coveting what we don’t have and what others have, stokes the flame of desire and before we know it, we are down the road of idolatry and over time given over to immorality. The god of Mammon, the god of money is the most common idol of our times, and we serve this idol thinking it can satisfy the unsatisfiable coveting of our lustful human hearts. How merciful God is that He does give us over completely! </p>
<p class="p2">Let us, as Paul exhorts in this verse, consider the members of our earthly body as dead to greed. How this translates into practical application could mean primarily keeping the mind free of coveting what God in his wisdom has chosen not to give us yet. Of keeping our hands reaching out for more money to buy more things. Of choosing not to use our limited time and resources in the pursuit of the world’s goods at the cost of our physical and spiritual health and relationships. Keep guard just as the<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>apostle John wrote in 1 John 5:21: <i>“Little children, guard yourselves from idols.”</i></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/about/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/about/</id>

        <updated>2020-04-19T19:06:35+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Opheleo is a Greek word which means blessing. What is blessing? Blessing is the opposite of curse and is generally taken to mean a bestowal of good. Blessings can take many forms, most commonly the form of words spoken or written to someone that foretell good, inspire, and encourage. What does this site contain? The site contains a collection of short posts, or longer essays - primarily mediations and thoughts on various portions of God’s holy Word - the Bible. The author hopes that these will in someway or other be a blessing to all who read, especially Christians. Who&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Opheleo is a Greek word which means blessing.</p>
<p>What is blessing? Blessing is the opposite of curse and is generally taken to mean a bestowal of good. Blessings can take many forms, most commonly the form of words spoken or written to someone that foretell good, inspire, and encourage. What does this site contain? The site contains a collection of short posts, or longer essays - primarily mediations and thoughts on various portions of God’s holy Word - the Bible. The author hopes that these will in someway or other be a blessing to all who read, especially Christians. Who is the author of these posts? He goes by the pen name Baruch Who is Baruch? The biblical Baruch was a faithful attendant of the Israelite prophet Jeremiah (626 - 587 BC), and was primarily known for writing down his master’s prophecies and reading them to people. The Baruch who maintains this site is not as faithful as his biblical namesake, but seeks to serve his own master, the Lord Jesus Christ through his writing. Why does Baruch write here? Baruch is simply a Christian believer who desires to grow in his faith as he reads God’s Word and also desires to share what he gleans from his readings so as to bless and encourage fellow believers across the world who chance to stumble across this site. The apostle John wrote ”These things we write, so that our joy may be made complete.” Baruch also desires an experience of similar joy through the exercise of writing, as he shares what he learns along the pathway of Christian experience, . Who is a believer? What does a believer believe in? A believer is one who believes that Jesus Christ is the son of God, who took on human form and appeared on the face of planet earth sometime in the middle of its tortured history to become a sinless sacrifice that atones for the sins of mankind. A believer believes that Jesus Christ was crucified, and through that death by crucifixion paid the price of redemption that quenched God’s holy wrath towards sinners. A believer believes that Jesus Christ not only died but also rose from the dead, and is now seated at the right hand of God as King of Kings and Lord of Lords. A believer also believes that unlike His first appearance, the Lord Jesus Christ will come again, this time in all His glory and power to execute judgment on this perishing and sinful world, and only those who have put their faith in the redeeming power of His sacrifice will escape the eternal punishment of God’s wrath. What is sin and why God so angry? Do believers really believe all this stuff? Where does all this come from? Yes they do. The believe because the Bible says so and because God has put faith into their hearts to believe what the Bible says. But explaining the entire nature of a believer’s belief is beyond the scope of this FAQ. Do reach out to Baruch who will attempt to clarify any queries or doubts you wish to get answered. Do also go through the posts on this site which may be helpful. Better still try and get your hands on a copy of the Bible which contains truth that is eternal. A good place to start reading the Bible would be the section called gospel of John. One verse that is really helpful in understanding the crux of Baruch’s belief is found in John chapter 6 and verse 16: “For God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son, that whoever believes in Him shall not perish, but have eternal life.” You can reach out to Baruch through the comments sections beneath each post, or by using the contact form here.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Home</title>
        <author>
            <name>Iraxel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://opheleo.cf/home/"/>
        <id>https://opheleo.cf/home/</id>

        <updated>2020-04-19T16:55:30+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is the home page
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                This is the home page
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
